<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Numb. 86 The curranto this weeke from Holland</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1639</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08149</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18507.313</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116934</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852149</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852149</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17458</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08149)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17458)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1382:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Numb. 86 The curranto this weeke from Holland</title>
                  <author>Hilten, Jan van. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>345-348 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by T. Harper?] for Nath. Butter and Nic. Bourne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Iune 21, 1639 with permission.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>The last of the 10th series of newbooks issud by Butter and Bourne, Dec. 20, 1638-June 21, 1639; pagination and register is continuous throughout the entire series of 100 numbers.</note>
                  <note>All but the final new item of the issue are translated from number 24 of the Dutch corantos of Jan van Hilten--Dahl.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 13571.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 13571 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Thirty Years' War, 1618-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:17458:1"/>
            <pb n="345" facs="tcp:17458:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Numb.</hi> 86 <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE CVRRANTO this weeke from <hi>Holland.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Containing, <hi>The paſſages of the</hi> French <hi>and</hi> Spaniards <hi>in the</hi> Low-coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, <hi>at</hi> 2 <hi>Siedges of the</hi> French. <hi>The landing of the Prince of</hi> Orange <hi>his Army in</hi> Flanders, <hi>neere</hi> Philip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines <hi>Sconce. The taking of</hi> 13 Holland <hi>Pinches, which came from</hi> Graveſend, <hi>by</hi> 9 Dunkerck <hi>Men of warre lately.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="letters">
               <head>From the Campe of Monſieur de Mileraye before <hi>Heſdin</hi> the 22 of May, the 1 of June.</head>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He 9. 19. of this moneth we came with our Army before this City: about noone the beſieged ſallied forth with 100 hoſemen, and entertained a ſmall skirmiſh; From the 10. 20 to the 14. 24 of this moneth, the Boores which were preſſ'd hereabout, laboured ſo ſtrongly in the trenches, that the 15. 25 of this moneth we lay fully entrenched; This Campe is divided into 2 Head-quarters, on one ſide commandeth Monſieur de Lambert, and on th'other ſide Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell Gaſſion: The beſieged ſhoot fiercely with their Canons; the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners relate, that they have about 50 peeces of Ordnances in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and 9 companies of Souldiers for a garriſon, and betweene 5 and 600 Peaſants: The City is fortified with 6 good Bulwarkes with a halfe-Moone Conterſcharpe, and a broad moate full of water, other fortifications it needs not, becauſe on one ſide of it is nothing elſe but Quickmire, notwithſtanding we have good hope to maſter it. The 14 24 and 15. 25 the Canons were brought upon the batteries: The be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged ſhoot fiercely with their Muſquets; in the ſaid City comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the Count of Hanapes, betwixt him and an Italian Gentleman, who was ſent thither by the Cardinall Infante, is great ſtrife and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie; the priſoners relate, that a great fault was committed here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, that certaine dayes agoe they did ſend a good part of the garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon towards St. Omaer.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Dunkerk</hi> 
                           <date>the 22 of May, the 1 of June.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </opener>
                     <p>At Newport is brought up Laurence Claes of Horn laden with ſalt, and here are brought up divers others, amongſt which is a Hambo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough
<pb n="346" facs="tcp:17458:2"/>ſhip of Gotterblock, laden with yron and Saltpeter, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with Dealeboards, <hi>Item</hi> 2 Boyers with limber and Steele. This day are gone to Sea 9 particular Fregats carying from 16 to 32 pieces of Ordnances, and from 80. to 100 men. Marquis de Fuentes, who lies with the Spaniſh Army, betwixt this City and Borborck, is to go towards Heſdin to raiſe the ſiedge.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Ryſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ll</hi> 
                           <date>the 24 of May the 3 of June.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </opener>
                     <p>Laſt Tueſday about 8 of clock in the morning, the French begun to batter Heſdin with 9 peeces of Ordnances, which they continued all the next day af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>er. Our Army is to march in two parts, one towards Boloigne, to burne the Country, and th'other part towards Tourane: Yeſterday the Cardinall Infante went from hence towards Arien, with many Earles and Lords, with whom he hath kept two dayes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether Counſell of Warre.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Cobl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>niz</hi> 
                           <date>the 24 of May the 3 of June.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </opener>
                     <p>Laſt Fryday the French Army conſiſting of 15000 men, under the command of Monſieur de Fequires, came before Thionville or Die<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denhofen on the River of Moſel, 4 leagues below Metz, and in the ſurrounding of it, they skirmiſh'd certaine houres long with the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perialiſts, amongſt which were 5 Companies of Crabats, and forced them to retire towards Tryer in a great diſorder. The ſaid Fort of Thionville is exceeding ſtrong, but by all app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rance it is not well victuall'd, becauſe at Collen lie yet 16 quarters of corne, which the Spaniards had bought for the ſaid Fort, and at Tries lie 1300 quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters more, bought for the ſaid Fort; this is bad newes for the whole River of Moſel and Rhyne. Marquis de Grana and Piccolomini lye yet about S. Vit, where they expect 12 peeces of Ordnances, and then they are reſolved to encounter the French. Conte de Guebrian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines in the French-county to continue the war there, and hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the Caſtle of Villano and other places; the Regiments of Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell Roſa and Canofsky, which lead the Avantguard, had almoſt ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken priſoner the Duke of Loraine, who had brought 500 quarters of corne into Diedenhofen and was comming back again from thence: many are of opinion, that Duke Bernard of Weymar will likewiſe go that way, which cauſeth great feare here abouts.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Mastricht</hi> 
                           <date>the 25 of May, the 4 of June.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </opener>
                     <p>Laſt Sunday and Munday about the euening, went out of this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty all our Horſemen and 300 foot with fire-locks, their deſigne was againſt the Village of Linter on the other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>de of the River of Demer, our Horſemen lay on the River de Gete in waite for the Horſemen of
<pb n="347" facs="tcp:17458:2"/>Thienen, Leuven and Hanuyt, which are about 5 Companies ſtrong, which came not once to light; our Souldiers burned down in the ſaid Village all ſtables and houſes, and brought along back with them 100 Cowes, and 134 Sheepe, the Boores had fled into the Church, this invaſion will make the Villages contribute, whether they will or not, they labour here yet ſtrongly in the new fortifications.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Bruſſell</hi> 
                           <date>the 25 of May, the 4 of June.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </opener>
                     <p>The Spaniſh forces in Italy have likewiſe taken the Caſtle of Aſty and lye now before the Caſtle of Ruſſignan in Montferat. The Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall de la Valette was yet at Turino, and had ſecured Cazall with 400 Horſemen. The Duke of Longueville had received expreſſe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to march in all haſte with his Army towards Savoy.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Collen</hi> 
                           <date>the 29 of May, the 8 of June.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </opener>
                     <p>Duke Bernard of Weymar cauſeth at Bryſlack many peeces of Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and a great ſtore of powder and ſhot to be embarked. Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell Oheim hath taken by aſſault the City of S. Claude, and ſlaine 300 men in it; by which meanes the paſſage is now ſtop'd, that the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards can bring no troops into the French-county.</p>
                     <p>The Duke of Bavaria demaunds monethly of the City of Ulme 80000 Florens, during the ſpace of 6 moneths. The ſaid Duke hath given order to Generall Sergent Major Mercy, to march towards the Lake of Conſtance and to joyne with thoſe troops which are to come out of Italy under the command of Don Franciſco di Melo Vice Roy of Sicily, they write of 12000 men, they are to recover againe the French-county and Alſatia.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div type="letters">
               <head>From the Campe of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> neare the Sconce <hi>Tervoren,</hi> the 30 of May, the 9 of June.</head>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>The Prince of Orange lies ſick in the Sconce Tervoren, of the Goute and an Ague but doth now mend again, and hath ſent abroad Commiſſions, that all his Horſemen ſhall come hither, in ſo much that we ſhall march forward within few dayes. Upon the River of Maaſe, Wael and Rhyne, all ſhips are arreſted, as alſo at Dort, Zee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, yea as far as Holland, the leaſt of 16 tuns; all the Souldiers are embarked into ſmall ſhips. The Lord Commiſſary Bockhoven hath received ſpeedy order to make the diviſion of the Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ine: the great ſhip brid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e lies at the Rhynberg, the Lord Controller de Mylen is gone to the Boſh to muſter all the Wagons and Horſes for the Train. Count William of Naſſaw Field Marſhall, and Count Henry Caſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mir are likewiſe here, our Horſemen lie in the little Country of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſtin, every one is charged to keepe himſelfe in readineſſe to march forward.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <pb facs="tcp:17458:3"/>
                     <opener>
                        <dateline>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </dateline>
                     </opener>
                     <p>The 16.26 of May, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> lay the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>edge before Thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ville or D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>, and all things went on well at the firſt, but the 7 of this moneth now ſtale, Piccolomini arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with 12000 men, and fell upon him unawares, and being the French foot had received freſh pay, and the horſemen none, the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemen would not fight upon any termes, but betooke themſelves pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to flight, leaving the foot to the mercy of Piccolominies forces, and although the French foot fought moſt ſtoutly and had Piccolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minies Artillery in poſſeſſion for 4 houres together; Yet at laſt being Piccolominies horſemen came with great fury againſt them, they were totally routed and defeated; Monſieur de Fequieres was ſhot into the arme and taken priſoner; they miſſe of the foot forces about 3000 men, which were both ſlain &amp; taken priſoners, but of the horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men they miſe not above 200. At Verdun lay yet a Regiments of horſe &amp; 6 of foot, which ſhould have joyned with this Army, but they came to late: Marſhall de Chaſtillion is now marching with 12000. men towards the River of Moſel, with whom are to joyne the ſaid 8 Regiments, &amp; the remainder of the defeated Army to lie in waite for Piccolominies comming back. Before Heſdin the French have got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in 3 places over the moate, and undermine it now in 3 ſeverall places together, to morrow or the next day after the mines ſhall be blown up, and then an aſſault ſhall be given in 3 ſeverall places toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; the French King &amp; the Cardinall Richelieu will be there in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, the beſieged defend themſelves ſtoutly &amp; make great oppoſition.</p>
                     <p>From Dunkerck, Gant &amp; other places they write for certaine, that the Prince of Orange hath landed with al his forces about Philippina Sconce &amp; the Fort of S. Anna, it is thought, that he will beſiege T'ſas of Gant, which will make a great diverſion in thoſe parts.</p>
                     <p>The 8 of this moneth 9 Dunkerck Fregats tooke 13 Zeeland Pincks and Boyers, which went from Graveſend for Vliſinghen, in which Pincks were about 200 paſſengers, the Convoy or Man of war being overmatched by the Dunkerckers, was forced to ſhift for himſelfe as well as he could, and to ſave himſelfe by flight.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimatur <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for NATH. BVTTER, and NIC. BOV<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Iune</hi> 21. 1639. <hi>With Permiſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17458:3"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
